all right
uh you want to pick on somebody
yes
[Music]
all right
so the first person who's going to read
is
mariani
okay thank you
so i read the english
hang on one second let me change
something here
[Music]
hang on hang on hang on
hey
yeah how about you read uh
just follow me and we'll read this much
okay
if the body of a pleasure being really
did exist in truth
then they could never take a rebirth as
another type of being
and the five objects of the senses
appearing as they do to the attachment
to their heavenly form
as if they existed in truth
could never start appearing to be some
other way
in that case then how could anyone begin
to feel attachment to the other four
objects of the senses sound and all the
rest
if they did
then it would clearly be a contradiction
for the colors and shapes
they'd already been focusing on to have
really ex to have existed in reality
okay this is really hard and uh i'm
sorry for that but um
but what it means is very deep so
tim i was feeling bad that we didn't
cover more yesterday and if we go that
way it's going to take a hundred years
so
i'll try to i mean
maybe but i think people were really
happy with yesterday and the and the
question and answer so i wouldn't worry
about it but i say we take our time
all right
uh and we will have question answered in
45 minutes right all right
okay cool
um
so they're still talking about
uh somebody who was a very good person
in this life i'll try to slow down
translators i get excited in the morning
and because of that they were born as a
very powerful person very wealthy person
okay
and
even
even after they're reborn
uh they're still seeing things wrong
which is why they had to be reborn
okay so they
did good things
but they didn't really understand what
they were doing
they they thought
that the people they were doing the good
things for
existed out there and weren't coming
from them
so in this case it's interesting
uh it's the opposite of the
husband in the kitchen problem
so when you go to the kitchen and your
husband yells at you
then you feel
upset
because
you don't
understand
that he's coming from you okay you don't
understand it so you feel upset okay
uh
here's the opposite problem
so these people are
they did nice things for other people
in this life
they didn't really understand what they
were doing
and they felt that those people were
coming this way also
so now we get into an interesting
question
that it's possible
to do the wrong thing while you're doing
the right thing
so uh
in this case the person was very
generous to other people
maybe they gave way a lot of money or
something
but they had this same problem as the
wife in the kitchen
and they felt like those other people
that they are giving money to
that they also come from the outside
from this way
you see in fact
in the ancient books i'll give you a new
word
i think i
can do that let me see
yeah here's a new word for you guys
uh surtong
okay and uh sutong means uh
the person who sees the pen
is coming
this way towards them okay sotong means
they see the pen is coming this way
in fact they see everything coming this
way
and uh even themselves
and
uh they don't understand
that the husband's coming from them
but also the people that they are
friendly towards the people they love
uh maybe people in the kitchen that they
gave some money to them
so they did good deeds but we call them
dirty good deeds
and dirty good deeds means uh
you don't understand
that the money you have to give to other
people
is not coming this way
and that the other people you give the
money to
they're also not coming this way
so even while you're doing a good deed
uh you're you are
making a mistake
in your mind
you still think
the money you're giving
comes from
comes from the other side comes from the
the government money making factory and
you're thinking that
the person you give the money to
they're also coming this way like maybe
it's your mother or your father
something like that
you don't understand they're also coming
from you okay
so what happens to these people uh they
do
take a nice rebirth
but the seeds run out because they don't
understand
that the seeds are creating
the their new body you know
their
superhero body
in the deva in the in the land of
devadeva means like a
superhero body that you can get
uh if you're very nice to people i think
uh some traditions
when they talk about heaven
they are
maybe they saw something like this but
it's it's not a
real heaven because uh you can't stay
there
and the the karma wears out the seeds
were out
because you you were generous
but you misunderstood the person you are
generous to them
uh so
so again you don't understand that
things are coming from you and now they
they talk about something interesting
uh
if that deva
who is reborn okay
if he's not coming from seeds or
if she's not coming from
she's kind of sad because she cannot
enjoy
everything in in the deva temporary
heaven what do you mean
of course they are enjoying
they have great food there
probably they have donuts everywhere
and they are very strong and beautiful
in fact they are so beautiful
their heaven is called the the form
realm which means the realm of beauty
and uh
so guess what
what do you say there's a problem well
uh they can only see things
they can't hear anything
they can't smell anything
they can't taste anything now if that's
true it's not heaven for me if you
because you can't have donuts you know
you just see beautiful things and you
can't eat anything
okay and uh they can't feel anything
when they touch the other devils they
can't feel anything
and then the devil you know the devil
part of your mind it says no no
that's not true you know i heard that
those devas
they can throw planets you know
they can play baseball or soccer
uh with planets you know
and
of course they have to kick the ball
and uh they have to
drink some they have to go to the beer
garden
after the game right
so
i saw the one in the munich uh
guess that's not true of course they can
see things they can taste things
they can kick planets you know no no
they cannot
then why pension llama says no they
cannot okay
why
well because when they see things
those things they see
are coming from the outside
okay those things that they see
according to you
uh they are coming from the outside the
colors
and the shapes that they see
are coming from the outside now this is
very difficult okay this is very very
difficult
if color and shape
is coming from the outside
then it cannot change
okay if color and shape
are coming from the outside
then you cannot cheer to a beautiful
song
and you cannot shift to the feel of the
silk of the gods on your body okay
because
they don't change the color and the
shape
if they are coming from the outside
they don't change okay
and then of course you think well
gesture
of course they change you know the sun
comes out
the sun goes down
the moon comes up
the moon comes down even in the deva
realms you know things are changing in
nature
okay things are changing in nature
and the planets are moving uh that
doesn't depend on us
you know and then first panchayat says
think again
okay
you know
we like to use the word nature
my wife is always telling me we should
you should get off the computer stop
translating
go outside in the nature you know
get some fresh air
look at the rocks and the trees you know
she even went uh
two weeks ago she went a camping by
herself because she gave up that i would
go
and uh
and we call it nature right
in english we call it nature
and nature means
uh people didn't make it you know so so
my wife likes to go to the mountains
or the forest uh
and
she doesn't want to visit i tried to
take her to paris she didn't like it
she wants to see mountains and trees and
you know like that which is nature
and then nature
if you think about it
nature means nobody made it right the
word nature means
uh she doesn't want to go to see the
louvre in paris because somebody made it
and it's full of things that
people made like mona lisa
you know and uh she wants to say
something natural
which was not made by people
but
according to our idea
it's not that uh 50 of the world was
made by us
it's not that
people made the cities
and then nature made the nature it's not
like that
people made everything
the living beings animals and people
they made everything they also made the
oceans
and they made the trees
and they made the mountains
there's no nature
okay what you call nature is not true
nature means nobody made it and not it's
natural right
but actually we made everything there's
no movement
now understand this
there's no movement in the universe
which is not coming from your mind okay
the the stars don't move
uh the sun doesn't come up and go down
the moon doesn't go up and go down
this planet doesn't spin around
from its own sound
so how much is coming from us
everything is coming from us okay
then if if what we see is coming from
from the outside okay
if the colors and shapes that if this
the blue sky
is not coming from me if the blue sky is
coming from the blue sky then i will
never hear anything
that's what uh pension llama is saying
here okay if if the blue sky
which you see with your eyes
is natural
and you didn't make it and it's just
coming
to you you know if the blue sky is
natural
then you could never hear anything
because
that that wouldn't be coming from the
outside it would be coming from you you
see if if nature is coming from nature
then
sound is also coming from nature
and it's not coming from you
if sound is coming from nature
by itself
then you cannot switch
from looking at something beautiful like
the sky
and then switch to listening to some
good rock and roll where's that
[Music]
yeah i don't know if that's legal tim
sorry
that
was just listening to it this morning
it's a good song about death you know
uh
anyway
what the pension llama says here
uh if if the world is natural
if the blue sky is natural
and it's coming from the blue sky
then you could never hear anything
because it wouldn't change there's no
reason for it to change
you know nature just does its own thing
it doesn't have to change
okay it's very interesting
okay then who's he talking about
oh he's still talking about this guy who
was
very generous in his life but he made
dirty good karma
and he has a lot of
superhero body
but unfortunately he can't hear anything
why
he cannot change why
he didn't come from seeds
he was just reborn
he came from nature you know he came
from nature so
this these verses
you have to understand they're talking
about
nature
okay mariana question
ready
what percent of the world
is coming from us
and what percent of the world is coming
from the world
everything is coming from us
hundred percent yeah
we have a joke and this year everything
one hundred point zero percent one zero
one hundred point seven percent
uh coming from us okay
uh
so therefore
if if if any percent
is not coming from us
uh
then then maybe you could start
listening to a song
after you're looking at a zoom call
uh okay if it's coming from the outside
but
if it's coming from the outside by
nature
you couldn't shift from the zoom call to
the to the rocker
okay
because there's no reason for it to
change
nature doesn't have any
forces there's no gravity
there's no light
there's no electricity
there's no magnetism
everything's coming from us okay
all right here's another one tim you got
another victim thank you mariano you
passed
it must be your great background from
diamond mountain okay
hey tim who's next i like your hair by
the way
thank you
all right
the next victim is going to be
marcus starro
yay
here we go
oh by the way if you guys have it in
german or i don't know
any other language it's okay
okay
and when the being of pleasure gazed
upon their daughters
with that
version of love
that sees them as so lovely that love
would see what it sees
in a way that depends on nothing else as
something truly there
that way of things appearing is
something that could never
change to looking another way
and that would directly contradict
the fact that when these beings of
pleasure
battle with their cousins
their feelings change to hatred
if
these pleasure beings could begin to
feel hate
then
that would contradict
the idea
that their lovely love existed in
reality
and depended on nothing else
well nice okay by the way this uh whole
poetry here
is a special kind of uh
philosophy in the ancient books
and it's called the tapatas
hey tim i'll give you a hundred dollars
you had it recently
you asked me to look up the spelling
uh yes
do you remember unchanging right
uh that's another talk about this darpa
spelled differently it means um
means in theory
in theory
i think seiji said you put 100 reasons
down
oh
wait he did
in the chat
uh
no
that's right
means
okay if what you say is true
if what you say is true
then there's this problem this problem
this problem this problem this problem
okay that's why
this whole poetry here
uh in english has to say word
uh
okay a word
or could
because it's called uh optative it means
that the verb has to be
if if what you say is true
then there wouldn't be any love
and there wouldn't be any hatred
and there wouldn't be any wars you know
if what you say is true
uh okay so that's a special kind of
logic and it makes the english very
difficult to read and i'm sorry for that
but don't blame me i didn't write it i
mean i didn't write the tibetan uh
okay
so he says uh look
uh there's a kind of love by the way
which is called
ye
it's in the tibetan here it means
a kind of love
that when you look at that thing
they look extremely beautiful to you
okay so it's a special kind of love
i'll give a thousand dollars if anybody
can tell me
where that love is mentioned
thousand dollars that's on cabba's
mantra
no nice try though
that's love with nothing it sees
it's a shanti deva
no
okay
cancel the
bad it's in the seven
seven points right
seven cause and effect uh bodhichitta
development thing
hey don't tell me after i give the
answer that don't try to get a thousand
dollars out of me okay all right
yeah that's uh
one of the steps to develop bodhichitta
is to uh
feel like
the kind of love i mean
uh noor has from my tree i i'm so proud
of my grandson let me see
he was wha he was walking uh
yesterday first i don't know if it's the
first time but
it's the first time i got to see him
walking
and uh
of course i get uh videos about
my tree and and the other kids you know
like eva okay here you guys go
you ready
yeah he's just start walking we are so
excited uh
it means she doesn't have to carry
around 30 kilos anymore
uh
but uh
how the mother feels about her baby you
know why she sends grandpa
three videos every hour
uh
is uh
this intense love
and it's called uh young jamba it means
uh
the love which sees the child that's
very beautiful okay
so
uh when those davas
when they look at their own daughters in
heaven
who were born in their lab right uh
they feel this love
like nora has from my dreams she sees
the kid as extremely beautiful okay
uh
according to you
uh some percent
of that love
and some percent of those daughters
is coming from nature this way
some percent
of the daughter exists this way
and then i love the daughter okay so the
daughter's coming this way
and i meet the daughter with my love
okay all right my tree's
walking across the park coming this way
and then i feel love for for my tree you
see
and he says if if that's true
if that's what's really happening
and the people we love are i don't know
fifty percent is coming this way okay
then okay uh sansar is a good place for
the devas
they don't have any problems okay
according to you
they don't have any problems what's the
davis problems do you guys remember
they have one problem basically well two
three
they're always fighting with the
the demigods they're always fighting
there's a jealousy contest
all the time and then secondly they are
wearing out their seeds
because they were generous but they
didn't know why
and then thirdly they have terrible
death they have a very terrible death uh
when their seeds run out okay
now according to you
uh mr who's he talking to
the devil yay
over here the devil's over here the
angels over here
i don't know my head is in between
you know they are yelling at each other
and geshla is trying to think you know
then the devil said no no those
daughters
that they love my truth is coming from
my tree you know
and then the angel says no no
not coming from my tree my truth is
coming from us
you know then the devil says no no
mighty is coming from my tree you know
then the angel says no no if if my
tree's coming from my tree
then we would never hate anybody i
wouldn't hate vegetables
okay
my wife she finally gave up trying to
give me vegetables
you know
first she tried to get me to eat them
she put them in the refrigerator
and when i didn't eat them she throw
them out you know and then uh
we had a compromise uh
we have a big blender
and uh so i said okay every time you
make vegetables i i don't like them but
i'll i'll mix them up i'll put some
honey with them
we'll make it a milkshake you know and
then she said that's disgusting i worked
so hard on the vegetables you know
and and then you
so if it's true
that the vegetables are coming from the
vegetables
then i would never have any doughnuts
you see
if
if it's true that
my tree is coming from my tree
then i would never hate anybody
okay
it would never change
because it's not coming from me it's
coming from them
okay but we know that those
heaven beings you know davos they have
terrible wars with their
with the dead my god demigod means the
lesser cousins these are cousins who are
not quite so beautiful
and they are very jealous okay
so in other words
if any part of the world
was natural
your feelings could never change
from love
to hate
because the objects in your world the
children you see
and the enemies you see
they would be coming from their own side
all the time they would never change
okay
so your emotions would never change so
now we have two changes
uh
if if
if your son
my tree is coming from my tree
then
you could never listen to him you could
see him
but you could never listen to him or
smell him or taste him or touch him
because that would be a change
in nature
and according to you nature is locked in
and then
your love
would be the same all the time okay if
you had love in the morning
because you woke up with my tree
then the whole day you would never feel
anything but love for everybody
because
the the things outside
would never change okay why there's no
reason for nature to change
okay nature does its own thing all right
it doesn't have to change
the sky doesn't change the mountains
don't change
okay um
who's next tim
marcus are you playing music i don't
know
your son
some music okay
all right hey
let's go let's stay with our german
theme let's go to venice
microphone
and yet when these beings to look
upon their cousins the almost pleasure
beings and start to feel intense
feelings of hatred for them
that hatred itself begins to look as if
it too existed in reality
when the wars then come to an end
and the pleasure beings return to their
own lands
and the time too
returns for them to look upon those
divine daughters with thoughts of love
that see them again as lovely
well that would contradict the idea that
their former hatred had existed in
reality
and moreover if this perception of their
daughters as lovable could start afresh
in their hearts then that in turn would
contradict the idea that the lovely love
itself existed in truth
nice
again this is very difficult even in
english and the tibetan is quite
difficult because
it's all what we call the
if if
if what you say is true
then this would happen and this would
happen and this would happen so it's
difficult to translate and it's it's
difficult to read you have to
you have to think about it okay uh
if
then uh
this is a difficult point
so obviously when we meet somebody we
don't like
i don't know i i used to have people at
my diamond business
and uh
and i i don't like them and we had a big
building i think it was 12 stories
in manhattan and
i remember uh
when i come to work in the morning i'm
hoping
that i won't meet these people
i i guess uh sonam you had the same
experience in your company
you worked you you did a corporate life
also
so you come into the building and you do
a little prayer at the door and you know
i hope
they don't get in the elevator while i'm
going up to my office you know and
there's people
you know that you you don't want to see
and
to dislike those people
you are thinking
that they are coming from their own side
you see
the reason you don't want them in the
elevator
is that you you believe they are not
coming from you you believe they came
from the subway
unfortunately their train arrived at the
same time as your train
and uh you walk into the building
together and you walk into the elevator
together and
and you feel like uh
they are coming from their own side
and that's why you don't like them you
know you don't like them and it doesn't
change now this is going deeper
this these lines are going deeper and
you know we could talk about these lines
for
a week you know but uh
there's also this feeling in your heart
that the hatred is coming from its own
sun
okay that's what the first lines here
talking about okay
uh the person who came into the elevator
who i don't like
i it looks like they are coming from
their
and it looks like all the stupid things
they always say to me
is coming from them
okay
and then i start to dislike them you
know i start to
pray
that i don't meet them in the elevator
you know
and
and then you start to feel attachment
to the hatred
to the dislike
and you feel like
it's coming from the outside
somehow the hatred is also coming from
the outside and it cannot change
okay and it cannot change
if the person
that you don't like
at your job
is coming from their own side
and you meet them
in the morning in the elevator
then you should have
hatred all day
even when you go home and see yours your
daughter or your son my tree or or your
daughter or eva
okay because that feelings
are also not coming from your seats okay
so here it's a more subtle
uh
the person you don't like yeah the
husband in the kitchen who's yelling at
you yeah
where does he come from well guess what
now that i heard it from you for 3 000
times
i i believe the husband is coming from
his own side yes but where is your
upset mind coming from
okay where is that coming from
oh i don't know guess why when when my
husband is stupid i feel upset you know
yeah but try to understand uh the upside
feeling
is also coming from your seeds okay the
husband you see
is coming from you
and your reaction
is coming from your sins
and because of that
it's very difficult to escape sansar
okay your your natural
natural reaction
is not natural it's also coming from
your seeds okay
probably there's some people in the
universe
that if you call them stupid they will
love you anyway
okay
so
we have seats to
hear the husband call us stupid
but we have excesses
to get absurd
and it's not necessary
you know it's possible
that someone can hurt you
and you feel joy like when you see my
tree walking across the park you see
it's possible
okay if it's coming from you
if it's coming from the outside
uh
then
then when you get home and see your own
child
you should hate them the way you hate
the person in the elevator okay
if it's so these guys here in the
example here
they went to battle
with the other devas the little demons
who are jealous of them and always want
to fight with them
and
according to you guys
if if those enemies are coming from the
outside
and the enemy of my country is not
coming from me
okay
then i should feel hatred
when i think about them
and i should feel hatred when i get home
and meet my family i should feel the
same feelings okay
because it's not coming from me
so why should it change okay it's coming
from the outside it's natural
it's natural to dislike your enemies
okay
all right
and he has one more comment here
he said uh
the hatred they were feeling
when they went to war
uh and when they come back home
or the hatred you feel at work
for somebody in your
office if that person is coming from
them and not from you
then you should carry the hatred home
it should never change okay if it's not
coming from you
and
even if you could lose the hatred even
if you could stop the hatred
there's no logical reason
why love would start when you see my
dream
there's no reason why love would begin
when you get home so two kinds of
changes will not happen number one
your hatred will not stop and you'll
hate my tree
number two even if the hatred does stop
you couldn't start new love for my tree
when you get home because everything is
coming from the outside everything's
natural natural
okay it's not coming from you all right
uh and and what's the bottom line you
can only hate people
if they are coming from you
and you can only love people
and if they are coming from you there's
no reason to hate them or love them
you made them
you know
uh okay
it's very interesting
okay
uh it's very subtle i mean very very
subtle
all right tim you got another german
victim there let's see um i don't but
we're gonna move over to seattle
washington robert
let's bother
robert
i'm sorry for all the boogers i had
coveted this week but i'm getting over
it
my wife hey rob my wife told me uh
you can blow your nose on the zoom but
don't don't look what's inside okay
okay
[Laughter]
ready
yep okay
this method of implementing the concept
that things could exist in reality
is the same for every other thing in the
universe they simply could never exist
if a single state of our mind existed in
and of itself and none of the things in
the whole universe that ever appeared to
it could ever start or stop or go or
come
nor could karma and its consequences
even exist even in name
nice
uh
by the way tim i don't know how but the
translation is good uh okay
uh
so don't just talk about
the enemies of the devas okay
and don't just talk about that their
family members
you know they said
look my tree doesn't show up in your
life in the morning
from his son
and
the people you don't like at your office
they don't show up from their side
either and by the way
forget the people you like
and forget the people you don't like
nothing else either comes from his own
son so now he's like okay people you
do like don't come from their own son
your daughters of the demons
people you don't like they also don't
come from their own sign
like the demigods okay but oh and by the
way
if the people you like don't come from
their own sign
and the people you hate
don't come from their own side then
nothing else comes from its own side
either okay that's all nothing okay
and then inside
uh
even your mind
is not coming from its own sign okay and
that's important okay
it's not just that
uh
the people you love like my trees is
coming
from you
and it's not just that the people you
don't care about or the people you don't
like
are coming from you
even your reactions to those people
love
and hatred
they're also coming from your seats okay
so the outside world is coming from you
nature is coming from you
and then your natural reaction to hate
the people you don't like
and to love the people you do like
that's also coming from you and and
you don't have to live like that
it's coming it's coming from your sins
you can change your sins okay
if someone hurt you or hurt your country
it's possible you could love them more
okay
why
because the emotion reaction is coming
from you also
that's coming from
you know
there was a
you know i grew up in the christian
church and uh there's a prayer book
and
it's so beautiful it really affected my
whole life you know somebody
uh it's the most beautiful thing i i
ever read when i was young
uh and and some people said it was
written by uh shakespeare
and they studied it they studied it this
is church of england okay
uh they studied study study and then
they said no it wasn't written by uh
shakespeare it was somebody else and i
forget it's not crumwell but it's
something like that
and then they said this guy had an
interesting life you know
and they said uh
why
and they said you know jesus told people
love your enemies
the same as you love
your
family and yourself love your enemies
with the same love that you have for
your family and yourself love your
enemies
and then this uh bishop who wrote the
prayer book
he believed in it
and he really tried to do it you know
and there was a joke in england that uh
if you don't have money
hurt this bishop
try to become his enemy
because he's such a believer in in this
philosophy
that he will give you money every week
you know
he he so believed that you should treat
your enemies like you're like your
family
that if you are lucky
you can become his enemy and he will
take care of you
you know for the rest of your life you
know i thought wow that's so cool you
know so
the natural reaction
to your enemies uh
the natural reaction to people who hurt
us
it's also not natural
it's changeable
it's it's coming from your seeds and
those are old old old seeds because
they depend on misunderstanding your
enemy
okay the reaction
to your enemy of hating them
depends on
misunderstanding your enemy for
countless lifetimes okay countless
lifetimes if you finally understood
that your enemy is coming from you
then then it's possible you would really
love them okay then it's possible you
could love them okay
maybe even because they are your enemy
okay
and by the way uh if your feelings
couldn't change
then the whole universe couldn't change
and there would be no seeds that's how
punching llama ends this section
if your enemy is unchangeable
and if your feelings about your enemy
are unchangeable
then then we have to say seeds don't
work okay then then forget practice
forget buddhist practice just give up
okay if if
if enemy has to be enemy forever
and the people you love has to be people
you love forever
and if your reaction to enemies has to
be hated
and never love
then look nothing can change then just
quit
quit buddhist path why because then
karma can't change you know
then karma would always be the same okay
and and by the way if karma cannot
change
then it doesn't exist
even
from us
if karma cannot change
it doesn't exist
even coming from me
okay if karma cannot change if i cannot
change my reactions
and if i cannot change my enemies
then even cause and effect doesn't exist
all right cool
even even from me
okay if i cannot change
my hatred for enemies
and i cannot
change those things then i cannot change
my seeds okay
even
even coming from me even the seeds that
come from me
would not be changeable
and i would be stuck forever in the same
thing the devil would control my mind
and i don't know what the angel would do
she'd probably go somewhere else
okay
all right mr tim
where'd you go yes
uh let's let me get these announcements
out of the way because sometimes i
forget and i feel really bad afterwards
okay
show me either one i know we have we
have two announcements for you guys
all right here we go
here we go
okay uh this is a special project
at diamond mountain
and i i'm sad to say that we decided
because of the code in arizona is so
strong
we decided not to invite guests
this spring but i think by next fall
we're gonna
we're gonna ask if you'd like to come to
diamond mountain for retreat
but uh
last
november i think it was
uh we did a fundraiser
uh because we want to
we want to put trees back in diamond
mountain when
uh 150 years ago
the cowboys
cut down all the trees at diamond or
most of them
and we did a fundraiser in november
we tried to raise hundred thousand
dollars
to plant
i think three thousand trees and uh
we did it
on the last night of the retreat we
finished hundred thousand dollars
and that was the easy part
okay
now somebody has to dig walls and
put the trees in the holes and so we're
ready uh
you know you can still come to diamond
mountain all year
you can visit
you can do retreat
in fact all the sedona people are going
to do retreat tim i think it's april
and we're all going to do a one month
retreat there and you are very
welcome
to
scan this qr code
and
you're very welcome to come and help
plant the trees or you can send money
for more trees
okay
there's one more tim
uh these are all the new books
uh our our diamond cutter press has
suddenly exploded
and there's a commentary
to the heart sutra
there's a commentary
to the diamond color sutra
there's a new book on emptiness
meditations
uh there's a new book on the mind only
school translated by word
and there's a new translation of the
medicine buddha sutra okay so those are
five
new books came out
and this is the mixed nuts hard work
okay the mixed nuts are working really
really hard
they're as i said yesterday they're
working on 27 books right now
and i have to
say that we are getting results the book
uh
and also we have some sponsors from
austria actually and germany
uh have been helping some of the
translators and and i'd like to thank
them
and i'd like to congratulate you and
without the all project
we can't do these books anyway so that
all
gold clubs
in russian speaking countries and
different gold clubs
different clubs in german speaking dark
you guys are really really helping a lot
and because of your help
uh we are translating these books i
think
none of these books was ever translated
before okay it's it's very exciting
and they are very very deep books uh all
of kamala sheila's
meditation instructions are are in uh
udpala's book vanobel's book
on emptiness meditations the whole
meditation chart translation
explanation is is in her book
the golden key the red book in the
middle
i think it's the best mind only book
ever translated into english
and it's it's unbelievable and the
diamond cutter
suture commentary
and the heart suture commentary it's so
nice to have it uh
in your house just read it i like to
read at breakfast time
you know i actually put my computer on
the breakfast table and i
and i kind of just eat a slow breakfast
then
and i read a few pages out of some sutra
and
so these are all available by uh email
ebook no and you can get them
qr code you can get the book in about
two minutes
because of the hard work of rosa
fungrican
and ellie van der pass and also
we got good katie uh
in colorado so all these guys are
working hard and you can get the books
uh and the best
uh
foreign printer so this now these books
will be translated
into other languages like german
and that's all sylvia engelhardt
and her hard work
with the
bloom blomido blumenon publishers
and her team in hamburg and wherever she
is now i think she's in down in the
schwarze vault or something
uh
okay
but uh
you guys uh you know
uh she's printing uh more translations
than anybody in the world and i think if
you see sylvia
tell her she's doing a great job and
and uh they'll also be coming out in
german and russian okay
all right hey tim you got questions
sure i guess that um
one of the questions that's come in
recently by several people
is that once once i hear all of these
all of these teachings
i go to a place of extreme blame like
i'm just blaming myself for everything
you know my bad seeds ripen my good
seeds ripen
everything i see i just feel so guilty
and
just blame myself for this and what kind
of
how can we think about this and is there
some kind of way that we can plant seeds
to not experience blame while
understanding everything that's still
coming from us
yeah that's a great question that's a
really really good question yeah
and
i'll tell you the solution for this
problem
and if you get venerable ud palace
emptiness meditation book
inside there is uh a section about this
it's called low self-esteem right
except now uh
if you really understand first pension
grammar
then you should have super low
self-esteem
a new
higher level of low self-esteem
why
because every stupid thing in the world
is coming from you you know
oh my god
you know
i guess i felt bad before
i thought it was just my husband now
it's everybody
[Music]
you know in america our last president i
know i'm not supposed to talk about
politics but uh
but it was super depressing uh
to think we we create this thing you
know
and uh
so there's a
there's a discussion
in venerable udpala's book
about
what this same question you know what
what if i really understand
that all the bad stuff i ever see is
coming from me
i get overwhelmed
by
how bad i must be you know and then they
say
it's a special meditation technique
saying
hey tim i'll give 100 bucks anybody can
tell me what's saying
you guys don't want to make money
wait who said
i'm just waiting for the chat
um
that's too easy
i don't give money for easy stuff
this is okay i'll give you a clue
i know sunum knows it when you start to
feel
your mind is a little bit low in the
meditation how to bring it back up it's
called sanctipa
how to bring it back up
by imagining light
that's one way but that's not the one
i'm looking for that's called
think about some happy event in your
life yeah a hundred dollars for cinema
okay
cena we have a new system
you have to collect your own money from
ellie she's not gonna send it to you
okay you have to contact her
and say geshe-la promised me a hundred
dollars because i gave the right answer
okay uh because sometimes she's busy
uh
yeah so please do send her an email and
say okay here's my paypal number okay
yeah
means uh
look
it's
okay it's correct
every stupid person in the world
including america has a lot
it's coming from you okay it's your
fault
that's correct yes
but
every beautiful thing in the world is
also coming from you logically logically
okay
every intelligent person
every
kind person
every charity in the world
every mother who sacrifices her life for
her children
you know
every kind of love you see in the world
every all of it
is coming from you okay awesome
so yeah it's true
you created all these uh
crazy people want to have war or they
need power
you created those people
but
i'd say there's a much more good people
in the world that you also created you
created this
beautiful beautiful
billions of people
who quietly do kind things all day you
know
parents
who give up the the first 20 years of
the child's life in america
when the kid graduates from university
the parents
go on a vacation to europe
you know
so
you know the whole world is full of
parents right marcus who who gave up the
first 20 years of the
of their
children's life and and you created all
of those so
i think
uh it's correct
that there's more beautiful people in
the world
than there are uh bad people just the
beautiful people are not very loud
and the bad people are very loud you
know but there there are
billions of people sacrificing
every day for their parents or for their
children or
you know their ability they don't get
you don't see them in the newspaper
they don't get popular online
uh
but there are billions billions of them
and you created all of them
so
you know give yourself a little credit
saying
you know thanked upon me hey good job
just like
you know you created all those parents
wow
that's pretty cool
all right timothy we're going to take a
break
yeah
let's do one more question and then okay
i'm up for it i'm up for it go ahead
um
so
as we're listening to this you know
we're hearing that there's a debate you
know between a devil and angel in our
own mind
but the question is
how can i plant seeds to hear more of
the angel in my mind
i have a suggestion that comes to mind
immediately
and i understand the question
you know oh
all day long
and and listen we're all the same okay
the best person in the desire realm
and the worst person in desire
are about one percent different
okay
so if you're in this realm
you're messed up already okay just don't
worry about it
okay the nicest person in this room
and uh the worst person in this realm
are very very similar there's not much
difference okay
uh
like one percent or something okay if
you are stuck in this world
uh
involuntarily okay if you're not like a
emanation
then uh
then yeah the devil's talking in your
mind all day
okay
uh and the
and then just like god can i have a
break you know
like gestala even in the book the angel
talks sometimes
but in my mind the angel never talks
it's always the devil talking all day
long you know
how do i get more angel
in my mind you know
and uh
you guys know like i got married
not too recently
not too long ago
and uh
and my wife told me you know you're a
great speaker
i love to go to the
college and listen to you speak
and you speak almost all day
somewhere
but your listening is not so great you
know your your talking is
is good
but the ear needs a little more practice
you know
you're not listening very well sometimes
you know and
i have our feeling
that the angel is talking in our mind
uh
and we don't listen you see so i think
it's a difference
i think
there's probably a a rule
in the universe that the angel gets to
talk 50
and the devil gets to talk 50
but we have a listening problem you know
and and we we don't listen to the angel
she's talking
but we don't we don't try to listen so i
think that's something you can practice
in your meditation there's a special
meditation you can do
it's just called silent listening okay
so in your in your meditation
you can try it for fun
and it's just
silent listening okay and you you you
sit down
you take your eight-point posture
viral channel eight-point posture
and then instead of bringing an object
to mine
uh
you just listen
okay
and you say
try to listen for the angel okay like
just
open your ears
and listening becomes your object
so i guess it's a kind of uh fixation
meditation
okay so try it sometimes it's really fun
uh instead of choosing a
instead of choosing an outside object
like just sit down for 15 minutes
and listen
and you know you can hear
birds and garbage trucks
and and things like that
uh later you can hear your
heartbeat
uh later you can hear the
oxygen
molecules hitting your eardrum
and keep going deeper and deeper more
and more listening listen listen listen
listen
and then uh
you will start to get little messages
from the angel like she will whisper
things in your ear you know so and you
have to be patient
okay it doesn't happen after
one day or two days okay
you have to try it try it for a week or
two
and
just sit in meditation and listen
and first you'll hear all the noisy
things like garbage trucks or kids
or dogs barking
and
then go deeper deeper deeper
go to a place of silence
and then just listen and be open and and
i i say
you can start to hear
uh the angel the angel will say
beautiful small things to you
and it's a very nice practice it's a
very beautiful practice
all right tim grandpa's gonna go
go make some more coffee